<?xml version="1.0" encoding="us-ascii"?>
  <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
  <!-- generated by https://github.com/cabo/kramdown-rfc2629 version 1.0.30 -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC0768 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0768.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC0793 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0793.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2784 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2784.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3031 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3031.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5405 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5405.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6347 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6347.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6555 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6555.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6698 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6698.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7030 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7030.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dots-architecture SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dots-architecture.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dots-requirements SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dots-requirements.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.reddy-dots-data-channel SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.reddy-dots-data-channel.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1518 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1518.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1519 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1519.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5575 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5575.xml">
]>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>

<rfc docName="draft-teague-dots-protocol-00" category="std">

  <front>
    <title>DDoS Open Threat Signaling Protocol</title>

    <author initials="N." surname="Teague" fullname="Nik Teague">
      <organization>Verisign, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>12061 Bluemont Way</street>
          <city>Reston, VA</city>
          <code>20190</code>
          <country>United States</country>
        </postal>
        <email>nteague@verisign.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="A." surname="Mortensen" fullname="Andrew Mortensen">
      <organization>Arbor Networks, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2727 S. State St</street>
          <city>Ann Arbor, MI</city>
          <code>48104</code>
          <country>United States</country>
        </postal>
        <email>amortensen@arbor.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2017" month="February" day="15"/>

    <area>Security</area>
    <workgroup>DOTS</workgroup>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>


<t>This document describes Distributed-Denial-of-Service (DDoS) Open Threat
Signaling (DOTS), a protocol for requesting and managing mitigation of DDoS
attacks.</t>

<t>DOTS mitigation requests over the signal channel permit domains to signal the
need for help fending off DDoS attacks, setting the scope and duration of the
requested mitigation.  Elements called DOTS servers field the signals for help,
and enable defensive countermeasures to defend against the attack reported by
the clients, reporting the status of the delegated defense to the requesting
clients.  DOTS clients additionally may use a reliable data channel to manage
filters and black- and white-lists to restrict or allow traffic to the clients&rsquo;
domains arbitrarily. The DOTS signal channel may operate over UDP <xref target="RFC0768"></xref> and
if necessary TCP <xref target="RFC0793"></xref>.  This revision discusses a transport-agnostic
approach to this channel, focusing on the message exchanges and delegating
transport specifics to other documents. Discussion of the reliable data channel
may be found in <xref target="I-D.reddy-dots-data-channel"></xref>.</t>



    </abstract>


  </front>

  <middle>


<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">

<t>Distributed-Denial-of-Service attack scale and frequency continues to increase
year over year, and the trend shows no signs of abating <xref target="WISR"></xref>.  In response to
the DDoS attack trends, service providers and vendors have developed various
approaches to sharing or delegating responsibility for defense, among them ad
hoc service relationships, filtering through peering relationships
<xref target="COMMUNITYFS"></xref>, and proprietary solutions (<xref target="CLOUDSIGNAL"></xref>, <xref target="OPENHYBRID"></xref>).  Such
hybrid approaches to DDoS defense have proven effective, but the heterogeneous
methods employed to coordinate DDoS defenses across domain boundaries have
necessarily limited their scope and effectiveness, as the mechanisms in one
domain have no traction in another.</t>

<t>The DDoS Open Threat Signaling (DOTS) protocol provides a common mechanism to
achieve the coordinated attack response previously restricted to custom or
proprietary solutions.  To meet the needs of network operators facing down
modern DDoS attacks, DOTS itself is a hybrid protocol, consisting of a signal
channel and a data channel.  DOTS uses the signal channel, a lightweight and
robust communication layer, to signal the need for mitigation regardless of
network conditions, and uses the reliable data channel as vehicle for
provisioning, configuration, telemetry, filter management, and other unsized or
bulk data exchange.</t>

<t>The DOTS protocol is not intended as a replacement for such protocols as BGP
Flow Specification <xref target="RFC5575"></xref> or as a general purpose DDoS countermeasure
application programming interface (API), but rather as an advisory protocol
enabling attack response coordination between DOTS agents.  Any DOTS-enabled
device or service is capable of triggering a request for help and shaping the
scope and nature of that help, with the details of the actual mitigation left to
the discretion of the operators of the attack mitigators.  DOTS thereby permits
all participating parties to manage their own attack defenses in the manner most
appropriate for their own domains.</t>

<section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">

<t>The key words &ldquo;MUST&rdquo;, &ldquo;MUST NOT&rdquo;, &ldquo;REQUIRED&rdquo;, &ldquo;SHALL&rdquo;, &ldquo;SHALL NOT&rdquo;, &ldquo;SHOULD&rdquo;,
&ldquo;SHOULD NOT&rdquo;, &ldquo;RECOMMENDED&rdquo;, &ldquo;MAY&rdquo;, and &ldquo;OPTIONAL&rdquo; in this document are to be
interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>

<t>Terms used to define entity relationships, transmitted data, and methods of
communication are drawn from the terminology defined in
<xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-requirements"></xref>.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="architecture" title="Architecture">

<t>The architecture in which the DOTS protocol operates is assumed to be derived
from the architectural components and concepts described in
<xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-architecture"></xref>.</t>

<section anchor="dots-agents" title="DOTS Agents">

<t>All protocol communication is between a DOTS client and a DOTS server. The
logical agent termed a DOTS gateway is in practice a DOTS server placed
back-to-back with a DOTS client. As discussed in <xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-architecture"></xref>,
any interface enabling the back-to-back DOTS server and client to act as a DOTS
gateway is implementation-specific. This protocol is therefore concerned only
with managing one or more bilateral relationships between DOTS clients and the
DOTS servers, a signaling mode known as Direct Signaling in the DOTS
architecture. This is shown in <xref target="fig-proto-dir-sig"/> below:</t>

<figure title="DOTS protocol direct signaling" anchor="fig-proto-dir-sig"><artwork><![CDATA[
    +-----------+  signal channel  +-----------+
    |           |<---------------->|           |
    |DOTS client|                  |DOTS server|
    |           |<================>|           |
    +-----------+   data channel   +-----------+
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>The DOTS architecture anticipates many-to-one and one-to-many deployments, in
which multiple DOTS clients maintain distinct signaling sessions with a single
DOTS server or a single DOTS client maintains distinct signaling sessions with
multiple DOTS servers, as shown below in <xref target="fig-proto-mn-dir-sig"/>:</t>

<figure title="DOTS protocol direct signaling" anchor="fig-proto-mn-dir-sig"><artwork><![CDATA[
    +----+      +----+      +----+
    | c1 |      | Sa |------| c2 |
    +----+      +----+      +----+
          \                /
           \              /
            \   +----+   /
             +--| Sb |--+
                +----+

    DOTS        DOTS        DOTS
    client 1    servers     client 2
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>DOTS server Sb has signaling sessions with DOTS clients c1 and c2. DOTS client
c2 has signaling sessions with DOTS servers Sa and Sb. Except where explicitly
defined in this protocol, all mechanisms to maintain multiple signaling sessions
are left to the implementation.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="dots-communication-channels" title="DOTS Communication Channels">

<t>DOTS uses two channels, a signal channel and a data channel.</t>

<t>The signal channel is the minimal secure communication layer a DOTS client uses
to request mitigation for resources under the administrative control the DOTS
client; administrative control may be delegated.</t>

<t>The data channel offers DOTS clients a limited ability to manage configuration
and attack filtering for requested mitigations. The data channel offers DOTS
client operators the limited ability to adjust configuration and filtering for
their mitigation requests.</t>

<t>This document describes the DOTS signal channel. The data channel is defined
separately in <xref target="I-D.reddy-dots-data-channel"></xref>.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="signal-channel" title="Signal Channel">

<t>The purpose of the signaling channel is to convey DDoS mitigation request and
status information between participating agents (client and server or gateway).
Conditions during a DDoS attack are invariably hostile for connection-oriented
protocols traversing affected paths.  Mechanisms such as Happy Eyeballs
<xref target="RFC6555"></xref> may be used to select a transport suitable for a given time and
prevailing network conditions.</t>

<t>Implementations are required to support the DOTS signal channel over UDP as
specified in <xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-requirements"></xref>. This document therefore assumes the
the availability of a transport based upon UDP <xref target="RFC0768"></xref>, but also defines the
message exchanges agnostic of the underlying transport used to convey the
signaling.</t>

<t>Key tenets of DOTS protocol design are low communication overhead and efficient
message packing to increase the chances of successful transmission and receipt.
Desirable side-effects of efficient packing are the removal of the possibility
of fragmentation in addition to a message size that is friendly towards
encapsulation (e.g via GRE <xref target="RFC2784"></xref> or MPLS <xref target="RFC3031"></xref>).  Large UDP packets may
also be treated adversely by middleboxes with restrictive policies or may fall
foul of aggressive filtering.</t>

<t>In support of operational requirements for protocol efficiency, backward
compatibility and extensibility in <xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-requirements"></xref>, the signaling
channel uses Protocol Buffers <xref target="PROTOBUF"></xref>, also known as Protobufs, to define
message schemas and serialize messages exchanged between DOTS agents.</t>

<t>The security requirements described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-requirements"></xref> (peer
mutual authentication, message confidentiality and integrity, and message replay
protection are not discussed here.  However, these qualities must be present in
the transport over which the DOTS signal channel operates.</t>

<t>Key distribution in support of those security requirements to may be achieved
via the data channel, via an online mechanism such as DANE <xref target="RFC6698"></xref>, Enrollment
over Secure Transport <xref target="RFC7030"></xref>, or by out-of-band means.  The key distribution
mechanism is not specified in this document, but operators must take care to
ensure the distribution provides the same level of security demanded by the
signal channel itself.</t>

<section anchor="minimum-viable-information" title="Minimum Viable Information">

<t>DOTS is intended to be extensible and to evolve to meet the future needs in
communicating as yet unknown threats. However, it must be able to convey the
minimum information required for an upstream mitigation platform to successfully
counter a DDoS attack.  A client may have limited visibility into the full
breadth of an attack and as such may not be well placed to provide useful
telemetry. DDoS sources may or may not be spoofed and number in the millions.
Once mitigation is active, the filtered traffic seen by the DOTS client (or
elements informing the DOTS client operator&rsquo;s decision to request mitigation)
may not be representative of the ongoing attack. This provides challenges for
the quality and usefulness of telemetry and mitigation/countermeasure
stipulations and as such this type of information if conveyed can only be
considered advisory.</t>

<t>In these instances the minimum viable information required for the majority of
mitigations to be activated is that which pertains to the resource being
targeted by the attack (host, prefix, protocol, port, URI etc.), per
<xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-requirements"></xref> (OP-006). The DOTS requirements also identify a
mitigation lifetime period (OP-005) and mitigation efficacy metric (OP-007).
The former may be considered for inclusion in the minimum viable information
set, however, the latter may only be relevant in updates.  An explicit
mitigation request/terminate flag is also required: a mitigation MUST be
explicitly requested by a DOTS client operator.  Finally, each message should
include a message id or sequence number field as well as a field for the last
received message id or sequence number.  These may then be compared by the
endpoints to assist in tracking state and/or identifying loss.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="signal-channel-messages" title="Signal Channel Messages">

<section anchor="messaging-overview" title="Messaging Overview">

<t>The signal channel requirements in <xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-requirements"></xref> demand a
protocol capable of operating despite significant link congestion between DOTS
agents. In an effort to maximize the probability of signal delivery between DOTS
agents, all DOTS signal channel messages in the DOTS protocol are conceptually
unidirectional heartbeats sent between DOTS agents.</t>

<t>The result is a form of scheduled messaging between DOTS agents, in contrast to
a conventional request-response model. Once a signal channel is established, a
DOTS client begins sending unidirectional heartbeats to the DOTS server,
separated by the configured session heartbeat interval (see
<xref target="interactions-session-initialization"/> below). To request mitigation, a DOTS
client merely adds the requested mitigation parameters to its heartbeat, and
maintains that request until a heartbeat from the DOTS server indicates receipt
of that mitigation request. The DOTS server likewise sends its unidirectional
heartbeat on the schedule interval, augmenting the content of the heartbeat with
mitigation request status.</t>

<t>A simple exchange between DOTS agents with an established signaling session is
shown below in <xref target="fig-simple-session"/>.</t>

<figure title="Signaling Session with Mitigation Request" anchor="fig-simple-session"><artwork><![CDATA[
   Client                           Server
     |                                 |  // Active signaling session
     |<==== Signal Channel Active ====>|  // with heartbeat interval of
     |                                 |  // 15 seconds, +/- jitter.
     |                                 |
     |----------Heartbeat------------->|  // Client heartbeat
     |                                 |
     |<---------Heartbeat--------------|  // Server heartbeat
     |                                 |
     \                                 \  // 15 seconds elapse, during
     /                                 /  // which client adds request
     \                                 \  // for mitigation.
     |                                 |
     |----------HeartBeat------------->|  // Client heartbeat now has
     |          + MitigationRequest    |  // mitigation request params.
     |                                 |
     |<---------HeartBeat--------------|  // Server heartbeat now has
     |          + MitigationPending    |  // pending mitigation request
     |                                 |  // status.
     |                                 |
     \                                 \
     /                                 /  // 15s elapse, +/- jitter.
     \                                 \
     |                                 |
     |----------HeartBeat------------->|  // Client heartbeat maintains
     |          + MitigationRequest    |  // request as it waits for
     |                                 |  // mitigation to begin.
     |                                 |
     |     X----HeartBeat--------------|  // Mitigation enabled, but
     |          + MitigationRunning    |  // server heartbeat is dropped
     |                                 |
     \                                 \
     /                                 /  // 15s elapse, +/- jitter.
     \                                 \
     |                                 |
     |----------HeartBeat------------->|  // Client heartbeat maintains
     |          + MitigationRequest    |  // request as it waits for
     |                                 |  // mitigation to begin.
     |                                 |
     |<---------HeartBeat--------------|  // Server heartbeat, status of
     |          + MitigationRunning    |  // running mitigation
     |                                 |  // delivered to client.
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>All messages are variations of this scheduled heartbeat model. See
<xref target="interactions"/> below for detailed discussion of the message exchanges between
DOTS agents.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="message-definition-and-serialization" title="Message Definition and Serialization">

<t>The DOTS protocol signal channel uses Protobufs <xref target="PROTOBUF"></xref> as an interface
definition language (IDL) for signal channel messaging between DOTS agent,
reducing the number of discrete messages to just a single message superset per
direction, with function defined by the chosen fields contained within the
message.</t>

<t>Protobufs schemas are used to define the messages sent in either direction, from
which code may be generated for specific language implementations of DOTS. As
Protobufs serialization relies on numbered fields, signal channel messaging
permits the introduction of new numbered fields arbitrarily, adding the
requisite extensibility to the protocol while retaining backward compatibility.
Future revisions of or extensions to the protocol may use the data channel to
provide a mechanism by which schema updates or expansions may be communicated
during provisioning/session establishment.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="client-message-fields" title="Client Message Fields">

<t>Only the seqno and last_svr_seqno fields are required in every message, as
they are the minimum required for the heartbeat. Subsets of the other fields are
used to convey a given signal message type.</t>

<t>The fields in the DOTS client signal channel message have the following
functions:</t>

<t><list style="hanging">
  <t hangText='seqno:'>
  a client-generated sequence number unique to the message. The client
increments the seqno value by one for each message sent over the signal
channel.</t>
  <t hangText='last_svr_seqno:'>
  the sequence number of the last message received from the server, provided to
the server as a simple way to detect lost messages.</t>
  <t hangText='mitigations:'>
  a list of mitigations requested or withdrawn by the client. The mitigation
schema fields are described below.</t>
  <t hangText='active:'>
  indicates a request for a list of active mitigations and their detail that are
current on the DOTS server.</t>
  <t hangText='ping:'>
  an operator initiated heartbeat like message which will elicit a response
from the DOTS server.  This may be used to prove bi-directional communications
on an ad-hoc basis. For example, a DOTS ping may be used to prove keying
material on the DOTS client is valid and may be used to establish signaling
sessions with the DOTS server.</t>
  <t hangText='extensions:'>
  these fields may be used to communicate implementation specific details.  An
example would be the dissemination of filters between DOTS client and DOTS
server.</t>
</list></t>

<section anchor="client-message-schema" title="Client Message Schema">

<t>The DOTS client message schema is detailed in
<xref target="appendix-schema-client-message"/>.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="mitigation-request-fields" title="Mitigation Request Fields">

<t>The fields in a mitigation request are as follows:</t>

<t><list style="hanging">
  <t hangText='eventid:'>
  an opaque client generated identifier that distinguishes a unique event or
incident. May be used by the client as a reference to the specific event
triggering a mitigation request, or for other implementation-specific
purposes.</t>
  <t hangText='requested:'>
  signals the need for mitigation to the DOTS server. If true, the DOTS client
is requesting mitigation for the provided scope. If false, the DOTS client is
indicating it does not require mitigation, and the DOTS server MUST cease the
mitigation for the provided scope.</t>
  <t hangText='scope:'>
  the scope of the mitigation requested, which may be any of the types described
in <xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-requirements"></xref>, such as Classless Internet Domain Routing
(CIDR) <xref target="RFC1518"></xref>,<xref target="RFC1519"></xref> prefixes, DNS names, or aliases defined by the
DOTS client operator through the data channel.</t>
  <t hangText='lifetime:'>
  the lifetime in seconds a mitigation request should be considered valid.</t>
  <t hangText='efficacy:'>
  a metric to convey to a DOTS server the perceived efficacy of an active
mitigation, per operational requirements in <xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-requirements"></xref>. The
mitigation efficacy is represented as a floating point value between 0 and 1,
with smaller values indicating lesser efficacy, and larger greater efficacy.</t>
  <t hangText='extensions:'>
  these fields may be used to provide implementation-specific mitigation
details.</t>
</list></t>

<section anchor="mitigation-request-schema" title="Mitigation Request Schema">

<t>The DOTS client message schema is detailed in <xref target="appendix-schema-mit-request"/>.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="dots-server-message-fields" title="DOTS Server Message Fields">

<t>DOTS server messages use a subset of the available fields to convey the given
signal type, including additional relevant fields as necessary. The only fields
which may be common to all signals are seqno and last_client_seqno which may
be used to detect message loss or out-of-order delivery. When conveying
mitigation information, the server schema may bundle multiple mitigation status
datasets into a single message, provided this does not violate the required
sub-MTU message size <xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-requirements"></xref>.</t>

<t>The fields in the DOTS server signal channel message schema have the following
functions:</t>

<t><list style="hanging">
  <t hangText='seqno:'>
  a server generated sequence number unique to the message.</t>
  <t hangText='last_cli_seqno:'>
  the seqno of the last message received from the client.</t>
  <t hangText='ping:'>
  an operator-initiated heartbeat like message which will elicit a response
from the DOTS client.  This may be used to prove bi-directional communications
on an ad-hoc basis.</t>
  <t hangText='error:'>
  details of an error caused by a DOTS client request.</t>
  <t hangText='redirect:'>
  Populated with the details of the redirection target DOTS server, if the DOTS
server is redirecting the DOTS client to another DOTS server.</t>
  <t hangText='mitigations:'>
  a list containing the status of mitigations requested by the DOTS client. The
fields in the mitigation status schema are described below.</t>
  <t hangText='extensions:'>
  these fields may be used to communicate implementation specific details.  An
example would be the communication of DNS mitigation vip to the DOTS client by
the DOTS server.</t>
</list></t>

<section anchor="dots-server-message-schema" title="DOTS Server Message Schema">

<t>The server message schema is detailed in <xref target="appendix-schema-server-message"/>.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="server-errors" title="Server Errors">

<t>If a DOTS client message cannot be processed by the DOTS server, or for any
other reason causes an error, the DOTS server MUST populate the error field in
any response to the message causing the error. As the error response itself may
be lost, a DOTS client may continue sending problematic messages regardless of
the DOTS server&rsquo;s error notifications. DOTS server implementations MAY terminate
the signaling session after client-triggered errors exceed a threshold during
a time period equivalent to three times the session heartbeat interval.</t>

<t>The DOTS client message triggering the error condition is indicated in the
last_client_seqno value of the DOTS server message containing the error.</t>

<t>Error codes MUST be one of the following types:</t>

<t><list style="hanging">
  <t hangText='NOERROR:'>
  Indicates the DOTS server has detected no error resulting from a DOTS client
message. Implementations MAY omit the error field entirely when no error
condition is present. This value is included in the schema largely to adhere
to the convention that an error status of 0 indicates success.</t>
  <t hangText='INVALID_VALUE:'>
  Indicates the DOTS client included an invalid value for a field in the client
message most recently received from the client. The DOTS server SHOULD include
specifics of the invalid value in the details field of the error.</t>
  <t hangText='MITIGATION_UNAVAILABLE:'>
  Indicates the DOTS server is unable to provide mitigation in response to a
mitigation request from the DOTS client.</t>
  <t hangText='MITIGATION_CONFLICT:'>
  Indicates a mitigation request conflicts with an existing mitigation from the
client. The DOTS server SHOULD populate the error details field with the
status information of the mitigation conflicting with the requested
mitigation.</t>
  <t hangText='MALFORMED_MESSAGE:'>
  Indicates the DOTS client message is malformed and cannot be processed.</t>
</list></t>

<section anchor="server-error-fields" title="Server Error Fields">

<t><list style="hanging">
  <t hangText='code:'>
  a numeric code categorizing the error type detected by the DOTS server.</t>
  <t hangText='details:'>
  specific information about the reason for the detected error.</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="server-error-schema" title="Server Error Schema">

<t>The server error schema is detailed in <xref target="appendix-schema-server-error"/>.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="server-mitigation-status-fields" title="Server Mitigation Status Fields">

<t>The DOTS server message contains zero or more mitigation status messages, the
fields of which have the following functions:</t>

<t><list style="hanging">
  <t hangText='eventid:'>
  an opaque client generated identifier that distinguishes a unique event or
incident.</t>
  <t hangText='ttl:'>
  the remaining lifetime of the mitigation, in seconds.</t>
  <t hangText='bytes_dropped:'>
  the total dropped byte count for the mitigation associated with eventid.</t>
  <t hangText='bps_dropped:'>
  the dropped bytes per second for the mitigation associated with eventid. This
value is expected to be calculated by the mitigator, and as such is
implementation-specific.</t>
  <t hangText='pkts_dropped:'>
  the total dropped packet count for the mitigation associated with eventid..</t>
  <t hangText='pps_dropped:'>
  the dropped packets per second for the mitigation associated with eventid.
This value is expected to be calculated by the mitigator, and as such is
implementation-specific.</t>
  <t hangText='blacklist_enabled:'>
  Indicates whether a blacklist of prohibited traffic sources is enabled for the
mitigation associated with eventid. The blacklist is managed through the data
channel.</t>
  <t hangText='whitelist_enabled:'>
  Indicates whether a whitelist of sources from which traffic must always be
allowed is enabled. The whitelist is managed through the data channel.</t>
  <t hangText='filters_enabled:'>
  Indicates whether client-specified traffic filters are enabled for the
mitigation associated with eventid.</t>
</list></t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="interactions" title="Interactions">

<section anchor="interactions-session-initialization" title="Session Initialization">

<t>Signaling sessions are initiated by the DOTS client. Session initialization
begins when the DOTS client connects to the DOTS server port, 4646. After
connecting, the DOTS client establishes the channel security context, including
all necessary cryptographic exchanges between the two DOTS agents.</t>

<t>This signal channel specification is transport-agnostic, and delegates the
details of transport, including transport security, to transport-specific
documents. Regardless of transport, DOTS implementations nonetheless MUST
provide signal channel security meeting the requirements in
<xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-requirements"></xref>.</t>

<t>Once the signal channel security context is established, the DOTS client sends
a channel initialization message to the DOTS server, optionally including
signaling session configuration values; if the session configuration values are
excluded, defaults MUST be used for the signaling session. An example
initialization message setting the acceptable signal loss and heartbeat interval
for the signaling sessions is described in <xref target="fig-channel-init-message"/> below:</t>

<figure title="Signal Channel Initialization Message" anchor="fig-channel-init-message"><artwork><![CDATA[
    message DOTSClientMessage {
      1 (seqno) = %;
      2 (last_svr_seqno) = %;
      6 (config) = {
        1 (loss_limit) = %;
        3 (heartbeat_interval) = %;
      };
    }
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>The DOTS server MUST respond immediately by sending a heartbeat (see
<xref target="interactions-heartbeat"/> below) to the DOTS client. The signal channel is
active when the DOTS client receives a heartbeat from the DOTS server with a
last_client_seqno of a signal channel initialization message. Both DOTS agents
MUST begin sending heartbeats on the interval for the signaling session once the
session is active.</t>

<t>The following example assumes a DOTS implementation using UDP as the transport
and DTLS1.2 <xref target="RFC6347"></xref>. In <xref target="fig-signal-channel-init"/> below, the DOTS client
uses the default values for acceptable signal loss, maximum mitigation lifetime,
and heartbeat interval. The initial DOTS server heartbeat is lost, so the DOTS
client sends another channel initialization message after waiting for the
minimum heartbeat interval defined below in <xref target="interactions-heartbeat"/>:</t>

<figure title="Signal Channel Initialization" anchor="fig-signal-channel-init"><artwork><![CDATA[
   Client                           Server
     |                                 |
     |<- - - - DTLS1.2 handshake - - ->|  // Server listens on UDP:4646.
     |                                 |  // Client initiates DTLS
     |                                 |  // handshake.
     |                                 |
     |----------ChannelInit----------->|  // Client sends signal
     |          seqno = 1              |  // channel init message
     |          last_svr_seqno = 0     |
     |                                 |
     |     X----HeartBeat--------------|  // Server immediately sends
     |          seqno = 1              |  // heartbeat reply, which
     |          last_client_seqno = 1  |  // is lost.
     |                                 |
     \                                 \  // Session heartbeat interval
     /                                 /  // elapses.
     \                                 \
     |----------ChannelInit----------->|  // Client retries signal
     |          seqno = 2              |  // channel init message.
     |          last_svr_seqno = 0     |
     |                                 |
     |<---------HeartBeat--------------|  // Server immediately sends
     |          seqno = 2              |  // heartbeat reply
     |          last_client_seqno = 2  |
     |                                 |
     |<==== Signal Channel Active ====>|
]]></artwork></figure>

<section anchor="session-initialization-error-handling" title="Session Initialization Error Handling">

<t>If the DOTS client specifies invalid values for the signal channel
configuration, the DOTS server replies with an error, and may ultimately
terminate the connection if the client fails to correct the invalid values, as
described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-architecture"></xref>.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="mis-sequencing" title="Mis-Sequencing">

<t>In the event that the DOTS agent receives messages containing invalid seqno,
last_client_seqno or last_svr_seqno these should be discarded and ignored.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="interactions-heartbeat" title="Heartbeat">

<t>The most common message exchanged between a DOTS client and a DOTS server is a
heartbeat (OP-002 <xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-requirements"></xref>), which maintains and monitors
the health of the DOTS session.  This is achieved with simple, loosely-coupled
bi-directional messages containing the sending DOTS agent&rsquo;s message sequence
number and the sequence number the sending DOTS agent last received from its
peer. Due to the stress volumetric DDoS impose upon a network, a degree of loss
during attacks is to be expected. Message loss tolerance may be set on signal
channel establishment.</t>

<t>The default heartbeat interval is 20 seconds, plus or minus a number of
milliseconds between 50 and 2000. The number of milliseconds MUST be randomized
in order to introduce jitter into the heartbeat interval, as recommended by
<xref target="RFC5405"></xref>. The default interval is derived from the recommendations in <xref target="RFC5405"></xref>
regarding middlebox traversal, to maintain NAT bindings in the path between
DOTS agents.</t>

<t>The interval between heartbeats is may also be set by the client when
establishing the signal channel. The minimum heartbeat interval is 15 seconds,
plus the random number of milliseconds as described above. The maximum heartbeat
interval is 120 seconds (two minutes), minus the random number of milliseconds
described above.</t>

<t>Heartbeats are loosely-coupled, meaning each DOTS agent in a bilateral signaling
session sends DOTS heartbeats on the specified interval, but asynchronously,
without acknowledgement. Each DOTS agent tracks heartbeats received from its
peer, and includes the sequence number of the last heartbeat received from the
peer agent in the next heartbeat sent, as shown in <xref target="fig-heartbeats"/>:</t>

<figure title="Heartbeats Between DOTS agents" anchor="fig-heartbeats"><artwork><![CDATA[
   Client                           Server
     |                                 |
     |----------HeartBeat------------->|  // Client heartbeat
     |          seqno = 1              |
     |          last_svr_seqno = 0     |
     |                                 |
     |<---------HeartBeat--------------|  // Server heartbeat
     |          seqno = 1              |
     |          last_client_seqno = 1  |
     |                                 |
     |----------HeartBeat------------->|  // Client heartbeat
     |          seqno = 2              |
     |          last_svr_seqno = 1     |
     |                                 |
     |      X---HeartBeat--------------|  // Server heartbeat lost
     |          seqno = 2              |
     |          last_client_seqno = 2  |
     |                                 |
     |----------HeartBeat------------->|  // Client heartbeat,
     |          seqno = 3              |  // last_svr_seqno remains 1,
     |          last_svr_seqno = 1     |  // indicating lost heartbeat
     |                                 |
     |<---------HeartBeat--------------|  // Server heartbeat resumes
     |          seqno = 3              |
     |          last_client_seqno = 3  |
     |                                 |
     |----------HeartBeat------------->|  // Client heartbeat
     |          seqno = 4              |
     |          last_svr_seqno = 3     |
     |                                 |
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>The DOTS client heartbeat has the following format:</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
    message DOTSClientMessage {
      1 (seqno) = %;
      2 (last_svr_seqno) = %;
    }
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>The DOTS server heartbeat is identical aside from the schema type:</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
    message DOTSServerMessage {
      1 (seqno) = %;
      2 (last_svr_seqno) = %;
    }
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>Should the number of signals lost exceed the acceptable lossiness value for the
signaling session, the agent detecting the signal loss may consider the
signaling session lost. The default value for acceptable signal loss is 9,
which, when coupled with the default heartbeat interval, amounts to lack of
heartbeat from the peer DOTS agent for 180 seconds (three minutes).</t>

<section anchor="client-ping" title="Ping">

<t>There may be cases where a DOTS client or server operator wishes to trigger an
immediate heartbeat response in order to validate bi-directional communication
(e.g. during provisioning).  This ad-hoc triggering may be achieved by setting
the ping field set to TRUE. When DOTS agent receives a message on the signal
channel with the ping field set to TRUE, it MUST immediately send heartbeat back
to the ping sender. A ping reply MUST consist of only the senders sequence
number and the sequence number of the received ping. [[EDITOR&rsquo;S NOTE: rate
limiting of pings required?]]</t>

<t>A ping is identical to a standard heartbeat, but with the ping field included
and set to true:</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
       message DOTSClientMessage {
         1 (seqno) = %;
         2 (last_svr_seqno) = %;
         5 (ping) = true;
       }
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="mitigation-request-handling" title="Mitigation Request Handling">

<t>The mitigation request is the crux of the DOTS protocol, and is comprised of the
minimum viable information described in <xref target="minimum-viable-information"/>.  The
request may be augmented with additional implementation specific extensions
where these do not result in undue packet bloat.  The DOTS client may send
repeated requests until it receives a suitable response from the DOTS server by
which it may interpret successful receipt.</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
       message DOTSClientMessage {
         1 (seqno) = %;
         2 (last_svr_seqno) = %;
         3 (mitigations) = [
           {
             1 (eventid) = %;
             2 (requested) = %;
             3 (scope) = %;
             4 (lifetime) = %;
           }
         ];
       }
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>The DOTS server is expected to respond to confirm that it has accepted and or
rejected the mitigation request.  Upon receipt of the response the DOTS client
should cease sending additional initial requests for the same eventid.  If these
do not cease then the server may assume that the response was possibly lost and
should resend accordingly.  Acceptance status is communicated by the DOTS server
replying with the corresponding eventid and the enabled field set to 1 for
acceptance and 0 for rejection.  A rejection by the DOTS server should be
accompanied with an extension field detailing succinctly the reason (e.g. out of
contract, conflict, maintenance etc. ).</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
      message DOTSServerMessage {
        1 (seqno) = %;
        2 (last_cli_seqno) = %;
        4 (mitigations) = [
          {
            1 (eventid) = %;
            2 (enabled) = true; // Mitigation request accepted
          }
        ]
      }
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>After a period of time the mitigation request may expire and the DOTS server may
end the mitigation. Alternately, the DOTS client may explicitly terminate the
active mitigation by sending a message to the server that contains a mitigation
value with the eventid and that has the requested field set to false, as shown
below:</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
      message DOTSClientMessage {
        1 (seqno) = %;
        2 (last_svr_seqno) = %;
        3 (mitigations) = [
          {
            1 (eventid) = %;
            2 (requested) = false; // Terminate mitigation
          }
        ];
      }
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>The server must explicitly acknowledge the termination with a response message
with the enabled field now set to false:</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
      message DOTSServerMessage {
        1 (seqno) = %;
        2 (last_cli_seqno) = %;
        6 (mitigations) = [
          {
            1 (eventid) = %;
            2 (enabled) = false; // Mitigation terminated
          }
        ];
      }
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>The life cycle of a DOTS mitigation request resembles the following:</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
       Client                        Server
         |                              |
         |---Request(M=true)----------->|  // Mitigation request
         |                              |
         |<---------MitigationActive----|  // Server acceptance
         |                              |
         |< - - - - MitigationFeedback -|
         |                              |
         |---Terminate(M=false)-------->|  // Mitigation termination
         |                              |
         |<---------MitigationEnded-----|  // Server termination ack
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>
<section anchor="ancillary-messages" title="Ancillary Messages">

<t>In addition to the basic interaction, additional messages may be exchanged
throughout the lifetime of the mitigation. The following message types are
defined to provide requisite information between DOTS agents during an active
signaling session.</t>

<section anchor="mitigation-feedback" title="Mitigation Feedback">

<t>The DOTS server MUST update the client with current mitigation status. This MUST
include the eventid, and SHOULD include available dropped attack traffic
statistics provided by the mitigator. A DOTS server MAY provide feedback for
more than one mitigation in a single message, provided the resulting message
meets the sub-MTU size requirements in <xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-requirements"></xref>.</t>

<t>The DOTS client SHOULD use the feedback from the DOTS server when deciding to
update or terminate a mitigation request. For example, if the DOTS client learns
from DOTS server mitigation feedback that the dropped_pps rate is low, the DOTS
client might decide to terminate upstream mitigation and handle the attack
locally.</t>

<t>A mitigation feedback message from the DOTS server would resemble the following
format, assuming an active mitigation request from the DOTS client:</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
      message DOTSServerMessage {
        1 (seqno) = %;
        2 (last_client_seqno) = %;
        6 (mitigations) = [
          {
            1 (eventid) = %;
            2 (enabled) = %;
            3 (ttl) = %;
            4 (bytes_dropped) = %;
            5 (bps_dropped) = %;
            6 (pkts_dropped) = %;
            7 (pps_dropped) = %;
            10 (filters_enabled) = true;
          },
        ];
      }
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>
<section anchor="mitigation-lifetime-update" title="Mitigation Lifetime Update">

<t>The DOTS client may wish to update the mitigation during its lifetime.  Updates
may be to alter the lifetime to extend the mitigation, or an update may
communicate the perceived efficacy of the mitigation.  The former may be as a
result of the DOTS sever feedback which may suggest that an attack shows no sign
of abating.  The latter may be to notify the DOTS server whether the
countermeasures deployed are perceived as effective or not.</t>

<t>A DOTS client may update the lifetime of multiple mitigations in a single
request as long as the message size meets the sub-MTU requirement per
<xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-requirements"></xref>. The lifetime update message has the following
format:</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
       message DOTSClientMessage {
         1 (seqno) = %;
         2 (last_svr_seqno) = %;
         3 (mitigations) = [
           {
             1 (eventid) = %;
             2 (requested) = true;
             4 (lifetime) = %;
           }
         ];
       }
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>Upon receipt of the mitigation lifetime update, the DOTS server replace the
current mitigation expiration time with the new value. The updated lifetime MUST
be visible in the ttl field in subsequent mitigation feedback messages.  When
updating a mitigation lifetime, the DOTS client SHOULD continue sending the
lifetime update request at the heartbeat interval until the DOTS server&rsquo;s
mitigation feedback shows an updated ttl for the updated mitigation.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="mitigation-efficacy-updates" title="Mitigation Efficacy Updates">

<t>When a mitigation is active, a DOTS client MUST periodically communicate the
locally perceived efficacy of the mitigation to the DOTS server. This gives the
DOTS server a rough sense of whether the DOTS client perceives the mitigator&rsquo;s
deployed countermeasures as effective. The efficacy update update message has
the following format:</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
      message DOTSClientMessage {
        1 (seqno) = %;
        2 (last_svr_seqno) = %;
        3 (mitigations) = [
          {
            1 (eventid) = %;
            6 (efficacy) = %;
          }
        ];
      }
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>The DOTS server SHOULD consider the efficacy update an indication of the
effectiveness of any ongoing mitigations related to the eventid provided by the
DOTS client. The DOTS server nonetheless MAY treat any efficacy update from the
client as advisory, and is under no obligation to alter the mitigation strategy
in response.</t>

</section>
</section>
</section>
</section>
<section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">

<t>The DOTS protocol requires a well-known port to which DOTS client messages are
sent. The DOTS server listens on the well-known port for client messages. The
DOTS client binds to an ephemeral port per
<xref target="interactions-session-initialization"/> above. This document selects port 4646
(the ASCII decimal values for &ldquo;..&rdquo;: &ldquo;DOTS&rdquo;) as the well-known port.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">

<t>The DOTS protocol controls mitigation request and withdrawal and as such care
must be taken to protect against concerns outlined in the security
considerations of <xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-architecture"></xref>.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="appendix-a-message-schemas" title="Appendix A: Message Schemas">

<section anchor="appendix-schema-client-message" title="DOTS Client Message Schema">
<figure title="DOTS Client Message Schema" anchor="fig-client-message-schema"><artwork><![CDATA[
    syntax = "proto3";
    import "google/protobuf/any.proto";

    message DOTSClientMessage {
      // Client generated sequence number
      uint64 seqno = 1;

      // Sequence number of last received server message
      uint64 last_svr_seqno = 2;

      repeated DOTSMitigation mitigations = 3;

      // Request active mitigation list from server
      bool active = 4;

      // Ping request (operator initiated)
      bool ping = 5;

      DOTSSessionConfig config = 6;

      repeated google.protobuf.Any extensions = 999;
    }
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>
<section anchor="appendix-schema-mit-request" title="Mitigation Request Schema">
<figure title="DOTS Client Mitigation Request Schema" anchor="fig-client-mit-request-schema"><artwork><![CDATA[
    message DOTSMitigation {
      // Opaque client-generated event identifier
      string eventid = 1;

      // Toggle mitigation for the above scope
      bool requested = 2;

      // Mitigation scope as described in I-D.ietf-dots-requirements
      string scope = 3;

      // Lifetime of the requested mitigation.
      uint32 lifetime = 4;

      // Mitigation efficacy score as a float value between 0 and 1
      float efficacy = 5;

      repeated google.protobuf.Any extensions = 999;
    }
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>
<section anchor="appendix-schema-session-configuration" title="Session Configuration Schema">
<figure title="DOTS Session Conifiguration Schema" anchor="fig-client-sess-cfg-schema"><artwork><![CDATA[
      // Per session configuration sent on signaling session init
      message DOTSSessionConfig {
        // Acceptable signal loss
        uint32 loss_limit = 1;

        // Maximum mitigation lifetime in seconds
        uint32 lifetime_max = 2;

        // Heartbeat interval in milliseconds
        uint32 heartbeat_interval = 3;
      }
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>
<section anchor="appendix-schema-server-message" title="DOTS Server Message Schema">
<figure title="DOTS Server Message Schema" anchor="fig-server-message-schema"><artwork><![CDATA[
    syntax = "proto3";
    import "google/protobuf/any.proto";

    message DOTSServerMessage {
      // Server generated sequence number
      uint64 seqno = 1;

      // Sequence number of last received Client message
      uint64 last_client_seqno = 2;

      // Request immediate heartbeat response from client.
      bool ping = 3;

      // Server error details, if available
      DOTSServerError error = 4;

      DOTSRedirect redirect = 5;

      // Mitigation data, limited by MTU
      repeated DOTSMitigationStatus mitigations = 6;
    }
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>
<section anchor="appendix-schema-redirect" title="DOTS Redirect Schema">
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
    message DOTSRedirect {
      // Redirection target DOTS server address
      string target = 1;

      // Address family of redirection target
      enum RedirectionTargetType {
        DNSNAME = 0;
        IPV4 = 4;
        IPV6 = 6;
      }
      RedirectionTargetType target_type = 2;

      // Port on which to contact redirection target.
      // XXX Protobufs has no uint16 type, implementations
      // will need to sanity check.
      uint32 port = 3;
    }
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>
<section anchor="appendix-schema-mitigation-status" title="DOTS Mitigation Status Schema">
<figure title="DOTS Server Mitigation Status Schema" anchor="fig-server-mit-status-schema"><artwork><![CDATA[
    syntax = "proto3";
    import "google/protobuf/any.proto";

    message DOTSMitigationStatus {
      // Opaque Client generated event identifier, used by DOTS client
      // to associate a mitigation status with the event triggering the
      // mitigation request.
      string eventid = 1;

      // Mitigation state
      bool enabled = 2;

      // Mitigation time-to-live (lifetime - (now - start))
      uint32 ttl = 3;

      // Dropped byte count
      uint64 bytes_dropped = 4;

      // Dropped bits per second
      uint64 bps_dropped = 5;

      // Dropped packet count
      uint64 pkts_dropped = 6;

      // Dropped packets per second
      uint64 pps_dropped = 7;

      // Blacklist enabled through data channel
      bool blacklist_enabled = 8;

      // Whitelist enabled through data channel
      bool whitelist_enabled = 9;

      // Filters enabled through data channel
      bool filters_enabled = 10;

      repeated google.protobuf.Any extensions = 999;
    }
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>
<section anchor="appendix-schema-server-error" title="Server Error Schema">
<figure title="DOTS Server Error Schema" anchor="fig-server-error-schema"><artwork><![CDATA[
    syntax = "proto3";
    import "google/protobuf/any.proto";

    message DOTSServerError {
      enum ErrorCode {
        NOERROR = 0;
        INVALID_VALUE = 1;
        MITIGATION_UNAVAILABLE = 2;
        MITIGATION_CONFLICT = 3;
        MALFORMED_MESSAGE = 4;
      }
      ErrorCode code = 1;

      // Error details, returned as a blob
      google.protobuf.Any details = 2;
    }
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>
</section>


  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title='Normative References'>

&RFC0768;
&RFC0793;
&RFC2119;
&RFC2784;
&RFC3031;
&RFC5405;
&RFC6347;
&RFC6555;
&RFC6698;
&RFC7030;
&I-D.ietf-dots-architecture;
&I-D.ietf-dots-requirements;
<reference anchor="PROTOBUF" target="https://developers.google.com/protocol-buffers/">
  <front>
    <title>Protocol Buffers</title>
    <author >
      <organization>Google, Inc.</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2016"/>
  </front>
  <format type="HTML" target="https://developers.google.com/protocol-buffers/"/>
</reference>


    </references>

    <references title='Informative References'>

&I-D.reddy-dots-data-channel;
&RFC1518;
&RFC1519;
&RFC5575;
<reference anchor="CLOUDSIGNAL" target="https://www.arbornetworks.com/cloud-signaling-a-faster-automated-way-to-mitigate-ddos-attacks">
  <front>
    <title>Cloud Signaling: A Faster, Automated Way to Mitigate DDoS Attacks</title>
    <author >
      <organization>Arbor Networks, Inc.</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2011"/>
  </front>
  <format type="HTML" target="https://www.arbornetworks.com/cloud-signaling-a-faster-automated-way-to-mitigate-ddos-attacks"/>
</reference>
<reference anchor="COMMUNITYFS" target="https://www.cymru.com/jtk/misc/community-fs.html">
  <front>
    <title>Community FlowSpec</title>
    <author >
      <organization>Team Cymru, Inc.</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2011"/>
  </front>
  <format type="HTML" target="https://www.cymru.com/jtk/misc/community-fs.html"/>
</reference>
<reference anchor="OPENHYBRID" target="http://www.verisign.com/en_US/security-services/ddos-protection/open-api/index.xhtml">
  <front>
    <title>Verisign OpenHybrid</title>
    <author >
      <organization>Verisign, Inc.</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2016"/>
  </front>
  <format type="HTML" target="http://www.verisign.com/en_US/security-services/ddos-protection/open-api/index.xhtml"/>
</reference>
<reference anchor="WISR" target="https://www.arbornetworks.com/images/documents/WISR2016_EN_Web.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>Worldwide Infrastructure Security Report</title>
    <author >
      <organization>Arbor Networks, Inc.</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2016"/>
  </front>
  <format type="PDF" target="https://www.arbornetworks.com/images/documents/WISR2016_EN_Web.pdf"/>
</reference>


    </references>



  </back>
</rfc>

